Guide to the History of Medicine oversize print materials, 1628-1856 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
History of Medicine oversize print materials 1628-1856 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Medical Center Library.
0.5 linear feet Extent: 17 Items
The Duke University History of Medicine Collections acquire, preserve, interpret, and make available for research and instruction, materials documenting the history of medicine, biomedical science, health and disease in the global context of the Western medical tradition. The collection was assembled by Duke Medical Center Library staff, and contains newspapers and other oversize print materials related to the history of medicine. The earliest date comes from a modern reproduction in black-and-white of an anatomical treatise from 1628. Newspaper issues from the 18th and 19th centuries carry advertisements related to physicians' services, medical practices, and medicinal products. Single sheets from the London Illustrated News concern the activities of Florence Nightingale during the Crimean War, 1855-1856, and are illustrated with large black-and-white engravings; one issue reproduces a piece of music with verses praising Nightingale. The items were acquired from various sources as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
homprintmats
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, collection may contain materials to which the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form applies. Patrons must sign this form before using this collection.
Also, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The History of Medicine oversize print materials were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 2011 as a transfer from the Duke Medical Center Library.
Historical Note
The oversize print materials in this collection were assembled by Duke University Medical Center Library staff from a variety of History of Medicine Collections to form a reference and research resource. The Duke University History of Medicine Collections acquire, preserve, interpret, and make available for research and instruction, materials documenting the history of medicine, biomedical science, health and disease in the global context of the Western medical tradition.
Collection Overview
The collection contains newspapers and other oversize print materials related to the history of medicine. The earliest date comes from a modern reproduction in black-and-white of an anatomical treatise from 1628. Newspaper issues from the 18th and 19th centuries carry advertisements related to physicians' services, medical practices, and medicinal products. Single sheets from the London Illustrated News concern the activities of Florence Nightingale during the Crimean War, 1855-1856, and are illustrated with large black-and-white engravings; one issue reproduces a piece of music with verses praising Nightingale. The items were acquired from various sources as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Nightingale, Florence, 1820-1910; Nightingale, Florence, 1820-1910 -- Pictorial works; Advertising -- Medicine -- United States -- Periodicals; Anatomy -- History -- 17th century; Crimean War, 1853-1856 -- Hospitals -- History; Crimean War, 1853-1856 -- Pictorial works; Nurses -- Great Britain -- History -- 19th century; Military nursing -- Great Britain -- History -- 19th century; Military nursing -- Great Britain -- History -- 19th century -- Pictorial works; England -- History; Turkey -- History; Engravings; Newspapers; Sheet music
Related Material
Howard Kelly Collection of Florence Nightingale Prints and Photographs
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
History of Medicine Picture File
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Newspapers, 1783-1818
  Newspaper issues from the 18th and 19th centuries feature advertisements relating to physicians, medical practice, and medical treatments, including pharmaceutical products and tonics.
  - Columbian Centinel (Boston, Mass.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 27, no. 43, 1797, Aug. 2
    - Vol. 34, no. 6, 1800, Sept. 20
    - Vol. 36, no. 20, 1801, Nov. 7
    - Vol. 37, no. 17, 1802, April 28
    - Vol. 38, no. 16, 1802, Oct. 23
    - Vol. 43, no. 26, 1805, June 1
    - Vol. 43, no. 42, 1805, Aug. 3
    - No. 2478, 1807, Dec. 30
    - No. 2862, 1811, Sept. 11
    - No. 3335, 1816, Mar. 23
  - Independent Chronicle and the Universal Advertiser
    - Vol. xvi, no. 907, 1783, Sept. 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - United States Gazette
    - Vol. 53, no. 6799, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Other Printed Materials, 1628 [modern reproduction], (2 items)
  - Anatomical treatise from 1628, in Latin, reprinted in London, modern reproduction from 20th century, (1 sheet, 2 duplicate copies) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- London Illustrated News: features related to Florence Nightingale, 1855-1856 and undated, (3 items)
  - Miss Nightingale visiting the hut hospital at Balaclava, The London Illustrated News, 1855, June 23, p. 621-622 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    The large black-and-white illustration on this single sheet shows Florence Nightingale on horseback ascending a steep incline in the mountains of Crimea; she is accompanied by soldiers and porters both on horseback and on foot. The camp hospitals are visible to the far right in the distance. The short article beneath describes her movements in May and June of 1855 and her attack of fever.
  - The London Illustrated News, 1856, Apr. 26, p. 451-452 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Single sheet from the News features a piece of music lauding Florence Nightingale, covering a full side of the sheet. The three stanzas were written by Francis Bennoch (this piece of sheet music was also published in 1855 under the name Francis Bennock) and the score was composed by J.L. Hatton.
  - The London Illustrated News, 1856, Aug. 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Single sheet from the front page of the News carries a large illustration of the carriage used by Nightingale on the Crimean battlefields. The reverse side contains short article about the carriage and her efforts to help the ill and the wounded.